<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Musings of an Enlightened Idiot</title>
    <description>Gautham's personal blog</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>How Can You Subscribe To My Blog?</title>
        <description>&lt;h3&gt;SUBSCRIBE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; This site syndicates content via RSS (Really Simple Syndication) — which is an XML-based format for sharing and distributing Web content. Using an RSS reader, you can view data feeds from various news sources and blog sites in a central location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How So I Sign Up For RSS Feeds? What is an RSS Reader?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; To subscribe to RSS feeds, you need an RSS Reader (or Feed/News Aggregator). These programs (and services) will download and display RSS feeds for you. A number of free and commercial News Aggregators are available for download. Personally, I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://feedly.com&quot;&gt;Feedly&lt;/a&gt;. If you'd like to setup an RSS feed for your own jekyll-based github page, read this &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/en/articles/atom-rss-feeds-for-github-pages&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; What Are The RSS Feed(s) For This Site? &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/feed.xml&quot; class=&quot;icon fa-rss&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; All Posts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; &lt;b&gt;P.S:&lt;/b&gt; I lifted most of the content from the lunar baboon subscription &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lunarbaboon.com/subscribe/&quot;&gt;page&lt;/a&gt;. It's extremely clear and I'd like to reuse it. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 11:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//random/how-to-subscribe-to-my-blog/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//random/how-to-subscribe-to-my-blog/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charmolypi, Saudade &amp; The Maalai Neram (மாலை நேரம்) Connection</title>
        <description>&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Great music has a tendency to leave an indelible impression on us. They reflexively remind us of a person, place, memory, event, or feeling. After 5+ years (conservative estimate), I listened to this mesmerizing song again. It hit me right in the feels :) It spawned a lot of threads involving different, but related thoughts and memories. I've listed them as separate paragraphs and tied them all together in the end. Bear with my wordy account. I hope it's worth your while :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wrBeRs1vM4I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Sometime back in 2011/2012, during the first year of my undergrad, I was introduced to this song by my then roommate Naresh Balaji. I vaguely remember Visventh being surprised when I didn't know about this song. Apparently this was a part of the original soundtrack of the cult classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aayirathil_Oruvan_(2010_film)&quot;&gt;Aayirathil Oruvan&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, Selvaraghavan couldn't find a place for this song in the movie. Truth be told, I couldn't fully appreciate the song then. It was just a sad, melodious song to my ears. I had it in my phone for a few years until I upgraded to a better phone. Slowly, it just slipped my mind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Time flew by. My friends and I parted ways in the hopes of forging a better future for ourselves. We embarked on a long, winding, never-ending journey. It was all about chasing dreams. It's almost 4 years since we started on the path. Almost all of us are in different cities, trying to build a life worth living. I'm sure we all mean to stay in touch, but it's been getting harder and harder. Everyone has their own inner demons and everyday hassles to tackle. Life can be pretty exhausting I guess. But overall, I think we've put in significant effort to ensure that we don't drift apart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; My YouTube recommendations have been lit af recently. It's ridiculously good. I came across this song on my list of recommendations this morning. I couldn't help but smile involuntarily. I clicked the link only to be instantly transported to a different time and place. I was effortlessly reliving those memories. There I was again, 8 years back in Trichy, in a dusty, crowded little room (#33) in the Coral hostel at NIT Trichy. I could see myself - a skinny, pimply kid with glasses and awkward facial hair joking around with the best set of friends a guy could ask for. We didn't have a lot of money or resources, but there was no shortage of passion and warm camaraderie. We had big dreams back then :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; It's amazing when I think about how much has changed over the years. If I remember correctly, Naresh and I were the only 2 students in our hostel wing to own a touch phone in 2011! Maybe a few other did, but I'm willing to bet that it was less than 10. My parents bought me a cute little &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sony_Ericsson_Xperia_X8&quot;&gt;Sony Ericsson Xperia X8&lt;/a&gt; as a reward for making it into NIT. Naresh had a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nokia_5800_XpressMusic&quot;&gt;Nokia 5800 XpressMusic&lt;/a&gt; which was all the rage back then. We used to browse for pictures and download songs over a spotty Airtel 2G network. The hostel lacked WiFi, very few of us owned laptops, so watching a movie was a communal ritual. A large group would sit together to watch a movie chosen from a hard drive consisting of a large selection of pirated English and Tamil movies. It was also a time of brutal power cuts in Trichy that could last up to 12hrs. There was hardly any water suppy, but mosquitoes and countless insects were having a field day on campus. A pig sty would've been a befitting description for our hostels. Broken dorm toilet doors, dilapidated buildings and water filters, dusty grounds, cows sauntering around the huge campus, blistering heat, all this feels like a painful, distant memory. Yet, it encompasses some of the best times of my life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Now how is this song related to any of my ramblings? Well, for some reason, I remembered Naresh Balaji's Nokia 5800 as soon as I heard this song. After all, that was the first time I heard it. I've changed quite a bit over 8 years. I've had my own struggles and failures. A boy who was once a naive, optimistic, idealist has turned into a jaded, cautiously optimistic, realist. I finally have the maturity to truly appreciate the song. The bittersweet symphony of the song is just magical. Andrea's Anglo-Indian pronunciation of Tamil lyrics adds a certain charm to the song. All I could really do is sit in front of a lake or a river, listen to this song on loop and take a nice, long stroll through memory lane. As soon as I finished listening to this song, I sent a link to Naresh asking if he remembered the song. In his trademark style, he replied - &quot;Ha ha! Yeah da. அது ஒரு காலம்&quot; :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; This song evokes a two distinct sets of emotions related to - (i) the actual tone and lyrics of the song (ii) my previous life in Trichy. A major chunk of what I've been talking about so far is accurately captured by the Portugese word &lt;b&gt;Saudade&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row uniform&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/saudade.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; This word is starting to grow on me :) &quot;Saudade is a deep emotional state of nostalgic or profound melancholic longing for an absent something or someone that one loves. Moreover, it often carries a repressed knowledge that the object of longing might never return&quot; [sic]. To me (in this context), the faded, yet golden memories of youth is what Saudade is all about. It's finally sinking in that my friends and I are chasing different things in life and that our paths may not overlap as much as it used to. The following threads (not an exhaustive list) can be categorized under Saudade: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; my longing for things past &lt;/li&gt; 
    &lt;li&gt; my gratitude for all the experiences (good and bad) that've made me who I am today &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; a bittersweet smile when looking back at the unaltered past, at the idealism and folly of youth &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; a realization that those carefree, happy, good old days are gone &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; But Saudade isn't what the song is about. Saudade is a side-effect of my adulthood. It's a reminder that I'm held accountable for my actions and have an enormous burden of responsibility. If I have to describe the way this song (by itself) makes me feel in one word, it has to be the greek word &lt;b&gt;Charmolypi&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row uniform&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/charmolypi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; A beautiful word isn't it. It's perfect. It captures so many nuanced emotions. Charmolypi is a mixed feeling of happiness, while being sad. A phrase in the Tamil lyric - &quot;இது சோகம் ஆனால் ஒரு சுகம்&quot;, is the perfect translation of Charmolypi in my opinion (the primary meaning). Of course, with a song like this, it's inevitable that we'd go into memories involving exes and all the lovely folks who were once a huge part of our lives. But I won't talk about those cherished memories here. Some things after all are still meant to be private :) In hindsight, there were so many mistakes I could have easily avoided. There's regret and repentance associated with those memories. I've been horrified at my self-destructive streaks just for the sake of short-term relief. As misguided as it was then, those experiences made me a better person towards the end. Listen to this song, enjoy it. If this is your kind of music, I'm sure it'd evoke a motley of emotions. Hopefully, you have the time and patience to decipher your own thoughts and feelings. Have a wonderful day :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; &lt;b&gt;P.S:&lt;/b&gt; Huge thanks to Keerthana Manivannan for adding nuance to my post! She pointed out that I probably meant Saudade instead of Charmolypi. She's absolutely right based on the context of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gauthamvasan/blog/commit/e15dc9698afa32721dfe257d09130f065a3ecc6c&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;. I initially wrote the post partly as an effort to better understand my emotions. Conflicting thoughts and feelings are quite hard for me to decode. I believe I was experiencing a strange mix Saudade and Charmolypi while listening to the song. Saudade when it comes to my high-school and undergrad friendships, Charmolypi when I recollect some bittersweet memories the song evokes :)   &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2019 20:22:57 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//musings/charmolypi-saudade-maalai-neram/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//musings/charmolypi-saudade-maalai-neram/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Super Deluxe Trailer</title>
        <description>&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3-Xq_Zz3nPA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    ஒரு நாள், ஒரு ஆள் மலைப்பாதையில தனியா போகையில திடீருன்னு அவன ஒரு புலி தொரத்த... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    அவன் ஓட ஒளிய இடம் இல்லாம, புலி அவன நெருங்க நெருங்க, ஒரு மேடை தாண்டி சரிவுல பாஞ்சி, அந்த சரிவுல ஒரு மரம் இருந்தா... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    அங்க மரம் இருந்து, அவன் இலைய விட்டு, கிளைய விட்டு, கடைசில கையில சிக்குன ஒரு கொடிய பிடிச்சு தொங்க.... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    கீழ குதிக்கலாம்னா அதள பாதாளம், மேல புலி காத்துருக்கு... சரி இங்கேயே இருப்போம்னு அவன் நெனைக்கிறப்போ, அந்த கொடி மெல்ல அவன வளைச்சு அவன இருக்குன்னா....
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    அந்த கொடி மலைப்பாம்புன்னு தெரிய.... இப்போ அங்கேயே இருக்கலாம்னா, மலைப்பாம்பு முழுங்கிடும்...
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    என்னடா எழவு வாழ்க-னு அவன் மேல பார்க்க... அங்க ஒரு தேன்கூடு இருந்தா... அதுலுருந்து ஒரே ஒரு துளி தேன் நழுவி ஒழுகி, அவன் வாய் பக்கத்துல வந்து விழுந்தா... &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    மேல மரணம், கீழ சாவு... அங்கேயே இருந்தாலும் அழிவுனு எல்லா பக்கமும் முடிஞ்சுருச்சுனு தெரிஞ்சதுக்கப்புறமும் ... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    அவன் ஒரு நொடி.... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    பாம்பாவது... பள்ளமாவது... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    புலியாவது... புண்டையாவதுனு... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    உசுரு போனா மசுரு போச்சுன்னு... கவலையே படாம... நாக்க நீட்டி, தேனை நக்கி... 
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    ஆகான்னு சொன்னா ?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 20:12:02 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//cinema/super-deluxe-trailer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//cinema/super-deluxe-trailer/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>When Breath Becomes Air</title>
        <description>&lt;h3&gt; A Bit Of A Back Story &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; I can't seem to recollect how I first heard about Paul Kalanithi's heart-rending memoir &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/When_Breath_Becomes_Air&quot;&gt;When Breath Becomes Air&lt;/a&gt;. In hindsight, the whole experience of choosing this book feels surreal to me. All I knew (back then) was that it was a book written by a dying man. I made a mental note to read it later and just moved on. But the story doesn't end there. It somehow came back to find me at the right moment in my life. If I've learned anything in 2018, it's that timing is everything. Off late, I've been struggling to find meaning in life. Things that used to give me a strong sense of purpose no longer do. Atleast, they aren't enough to be sated. Unbeknownst to me, life had moved the goal posts already. What made me tick a year back doesn't work anymore. I need to reinvent myself and redefine the things that make my life worth living. It's almost impossible to talk about life and meaning without thinking about death. Nothing is more certain than death. Depending on your perspective, it could make life meaningful/meaningless. I haven't read/experienced enough to make a strong argument supporting either claim. But I do know that finitude (a word I learned from Paul Kalanithi) enhances meaning in life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;&quot;The dying are the ones who have the most to teach us about life...&quot;&lt;/i&gt; These words kept echoing in my mind as I rolled under the blanket, musing about a life well lived. I didn't know where I had read/heard that phrase, but I couldn't get it out of my head. I was experiencing the earworm reverberation. Finally, I had to google the phrase and et voila, I came across Paul Kalanithi, a great man whose life ended way too soon. A man who'd forever remain an inspiration to countless men and women including yours truly. A man who didn't avert his gaze when the grim reaper came knocking on his door. A man who's authenticity and integrity took my breath away. Quoting Lucy Kalanithi, &quot;What happened to Paul was tragic, but he was not a tragedy.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; Preparing Yourself Mentally To Read This Book &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;b&gt; Ecclesiasticus 6:33 &lt;/b&gt; 
        &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 
        If thou love to hear, thou shalt receive understanding: and if thou bow thine ear, thou shalt be wise,
        &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 
        King James Version (KJV)
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; This book has a lot of wonderful things to say. Question is are you prepared to listen? Some books are meant to be skimmed through in a rapid pace. There are a select few with which you take your time, carefully weighing each word, reading and re-reading portions you cherish. This book is just a little over 200 pages. I should've been done with it in less than 3 hrs. But it took me over 24hrs overall. Why? Simple. I was hanging on to every single word. I would sometimes read it out loud and let it ruminate for a bit. This book isn't meant to be a monologue. Give yourself some time to let Paul's words sink in. Listen to the voices in your head. They're all responding to Paul's beautiful prose-poem style of writing. It'd force you to dig deeper. A quick read to get a summary is a waste of your time. It's not a soap you watch to kill time. It's the tragic story you watch with your eyes wide open, unable to avert your gaze, experiencing a motley of emotions until something fundamentally changes in your moral core.
Abraham Verghese nailed it in the foreword:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    Be ready. Be seated. See what courage sounds like. See how brave it is to reveal yourself in this way. But above all, see what it is to still live, to profoundly influence the lives of others after you are gone, by your words. In a world of asynchronous communication, where we are so often buried in our screens, our gaze rooted to the rectangular objects buzzing in our hands, our attention consumed by ephemera, stop and experience this dialogue with my young departed colleague, now ageless and extant in memory. Listen to Paul. In the silences between his words, listen to what you have to say back. There in lies his message. I got it. I hope you experience it, too. It is a gift. Let me not stand between you and Paul.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; I highly recommend reading the following articles written by Paul first. Think of them as pre-requisites for his book. It mentally prepares you for the journey: 
&lt;ol&gt; 
    &lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/25/opinion/sunday/how-long-have-i-got-left.html&quot;&gt;How Long Have I Got Left?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://stanmed.stanford.edu/2015spring/before-i-go.html&quot;&gt;Before I go - Time warps for a young surgeon with metastatic lung cancer&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; What Happens To Your Identity &amp;amp; Sense Of Purpose When All Your Grand Plans Are Shot To Hell? &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; It's been a while since a book made me cry. Paul Kalanithi was no ordinary man. He confronted death - as a scholar, as a surgeon, and finally as stage 4 cancer patient. He might have died too soon, but he did not go gently into that good night. He's achieved more in 37 years than most people ever will in their lifetimes. What most people fail to understand is that he's competing on an entirely different level. It's an unending pursuit of perfection and self-realization that gives deeper meaning to life.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My brother Jeevan had arrived at my bedside. “You’ve accomplished so much,” he said. “You know that, don’t you?”
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    I sighed. He meant well, but the words rang hollow. My life had been building potential, potential that would now go unrealized. I had planned to do so much, and I had come so close. I was physically debilitated, my imagined future and my personal identity collapsed, and I faced the same existential quandaries my patients faced. The lung cancer was confirmed. My carefully planned and hard-won future no longer existed.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; A Life Well Lived &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt; As a neurosurgical resident, Kalanithi was well aware of the difference between living and merely surviving, the paradox and the interplay between the tough medical choices he's made and the things that give his patient's lives meaning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    While all doctors treat diseases, neurosurgeons work in the crucible of identity: every operation on the brain is, by necessity, a manipulation of the substance of our selves, and every conversation with a patient undergoing brain surgery cannot help but confront this fact…At those critical junctures, the question is not simply whether to live or die but what kind of life is worth living. Would you trade your ability – or your mother’s – to talk for a few extra months of mute life? The expansion of your visual blind spot in exchange for eliminating the small possibility of a fatal brain hemorrhage? Your right hand’s function to stop seizures? How much neurologic suffering would you let your child endure before saying that death is preferable? Because the brain mediates our experience of the world, any neurosurgical problem forces a patient and family, ideally with a doctor as a guide, to answer this question: What makes life meaningful enough to go on living?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; There's a certain alien beauty in tragedy and suffering. I sound like a psychopath when I say it out loud. But it's true. Bear with me. The kindest people have endured some of the darkest moments in life. The unexpected kindness of strangers in the face of unending pain and suffering is one of the hallmarks of humanity. Reading this book is like watching a tragedy of epic proportions unfold. He slowly reels you in. You know how it ends. Yet you are unprepared. A man who's achievements and passion evoke camaraderie and understanding in my heart. I know what it takes to achieve in his level. In a moment of pure vanity, I thought I was like him. Truth be told, if I live to be half the man Paul was, I think that'd be a life well lived. Amidst a horde of &quot;woke&quot; people forever harping on and on about living every day it was your last, here's a man who says something sensible :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    Grand illnesses are supposed to be life-clarifying. Instead, I knew I was going to die – but I’d known that before. My state of knowledge was the same, but my ability to make lunch plans had been shot to hell. The way forward would seem obvious, if only I knew how many months or years I had left. Tell me three months, I’d spend time with family. Tell me one year, I’d write a book. Give me ten years, I’d go back to treating diseases. The truth that you live one day at a time didn’t help: What was I supposed to do with that day?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; Struggle Toward The Capital-T Truth &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; I saw a few reviews mention that the book had nothing new to say. If you think Paul Kalanithi hasn't said anything that hasn't been said before (in terms of life lessons), you are right. But it also means that you haven't been paying attention. It's not what he said. It's the way he said it. The beauty truly lies in the eyes of the beholder. He's not the first person to talk about death, life and meaning; and he sure as hell won't be the last. For centuries we've had eastern and western philosophers discuss and debate about death and meaning. Personally, what struck me the most was Paul's unique perspective and undeniable authenticity. He was interested in discovering where “biology, morality, literature and philosophy intersect”. His whole life was built around those ideals. 
        
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    Struggle toward the capital-T Truth, but recognize that the task is impossible - or that if a correct answer is possible, verification certainly is impossible.
    In the end, it cannot be doubted that each of us can see only a part of the picture. The doctor sees one, the patient another, the engineer a third, the economist a fourth, the pear diver a fifth, the alcoholic a sixth, the cable guy a seventh, the sheep farmer an eighth, the Indian beggar a ninth, the pastor a tenth. Human knowledge is never contained in one person. It grows from the relationships we create between each other and the world, and still it is never complete. And Truth comes somewhere above all of them, where, as at the end of that Sunday's ready; 
    the sower and reaper can rejoice together. For here the saying is verified that &quot;One sows and another reaps.&quot; I sent you to reap what you have not worked for; others have done the work, and you are sharing the fruits of their work.” 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; An Impassioned Message For His Daughter That Brims My Heart With Love &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; He leaves behind this message for his daughter, Cady, eight months old at the time of his death. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    When you come to one of the many moments in life where you must give an account of yourself, provide a ledger of what you have been, and done, and meant to the world, do not, I pray, discount that you filled a dying man’s days with a sated joy, a joy unknown to me in all my prior years, a joy that does not hunger for more and more but rests, satisfied. In this time, right now, that is an enormous thing.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; Perfection Is A Never Ending Journey &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; He died trying to finish the book forever exemplifying his core value - strive for perfection knowing full well that you can never achieve it :)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    You can’t ever reach perfection, but you can believe in an asymptote toward which you are ceaselessly striving.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; In the immortal words of Samuel Beckett, &quot;I Can’t Go On. I’ll Go On.&quot; &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    And so it was literature that brought me back to life during this time. The monolithic uncertainty of my future was deadening; everywhere I turned, the shadow of death obscured the meaning of any action. I remember the moment my overwhelming unease yielded, when that seemingly impassable sea of uncertainty parted. I woke up in pain, facing another day – no project beyond breakfast seemed tenable. I can’t go on, I thought, and immediately, its antiphon responded, completing Samuel Beckett’s seven words, words I had learned long ago as an undergraduate: I’ll go on. I got out of bed and took a step forward, repeating the phrase over and over “I can’t go on. I’ll go on.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; Highlights &amp;amp; Comments About Lucy Kalanithi's Poignant Epilogue  &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    Relying on his own strength and the support of his family and community, Paul faced each stage of his illness with grace — not with  bravado or a misguided faith that he would “overcome” or “beat” cancer but with an authenticity that allowed him to grieve the loss of the future he had planned and forge a new one. He cried on the day he was diagnosed. He cried while looking at a drawing we kept on the bathroom mirror that said, “I want to spend all the rest of my days here with you.” He cried on his last day in the operating  room. He let himself be open and vulnerable,  let himself be comforted. Even while terminally ill, Paul was fully alive; despite physical collapse, he remained vigorous, open, full of hope not for an unlikely cure but for days that were full of purpose and meaning.
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Paul’s voice in When Breath Becomes Air is strong and distinctive, but also somewhat solitary. Parallel to this story are the love and warmth and spaciousness and radical permission that surrounded him. We all inhabit different selves in space and time. Here he is as a doctor, as a patient, and within a doctor-patient relationship. He wrote with a clear voice, the voice of someone with limited time, a ceaseless striver, though there were other selves as well. Not fully captured in these pages are Paul’s sense of humor—he was wickedly funny—or his sweetness and tenderness, the  value he placed on relationships with friends and family. But this is the book he wrote; this was his voice during this time; this was his message during this time; this was what he wrote when he needed to write it. Indeed, the version of Paul I miss most, more even than the robust, dazzling version with whom I first fell in love, is the beautiful, focused man he was in his last year, the Paul who wrote this book—frail but never weak.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; The quote above is important for context. Throughout the book, we see a side of Paul Kalanithi that he chose to reveal to us - a voracious reader, a gifted writer, a high-achieving scientist-surgeon, a man in pursuit of meaning and perfection, a man who placed a lot of value in human relationships. But that is not the complete picture. Lucy Kalanithi wrote the epilogue that concludes the book. Her account of Paul's final days is heartbreaking to say the least. When I was reading her afterword, I had to frequently stop to close my eyes and fight the tears. Her last sentences struck a chord with me:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    “For much of his life, Paul wondered about death – and whether he could face it with integrity. In the end, the answer was yes. I was his wife and a witness.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This book would remain close to my heart for a long, long time. I'm not who I want to be yet. Thanks to Paul Kalanithi, I atleast know that I'm headed in the right direction. Read this book. See what authenticity looks like. See what facing death with grace and integrity looks like. Listen to your inner voice when reading his immortal words. I promise, it'll make you a better person. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 15:47:48 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//bookreviews/musings/when-breath-becomes-air/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//bookreviews/musings/when-breath-becomes-air/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Excerpts From Surely You're Joking Mr. Feynman And My Thoughts About Them</title>
        <description>&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; &lt;b&gt;P.S: &lt;/b&gt; I throughly enjoyed reading the cult classic &lt;i&gt;Surely You're Joking Mr. Feynman&lt;/i&gt;. For my review of the book, please check this &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/bookreviews/surely-you-are-joking-mr-feynman/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;. This post is going to be quite long. I usually highlight my favourite lines/paragraphs in the books I read. For the first time, I'm going to list them in a public post and share my thoughts my about some of them. This is not meant to be preachy or a post on life lessons. I apologize in advance, if it turns out to be the case! I just need an easy way of accessing these excerpts whenever I feel like re-reading them :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; #1: Own up to your mistakes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    It would have been a fantastic and vital discovery if I had been a good biologist. But I wasn't a good biologist. We had a good idea, a good experiment, the right equipment, but I screwed it up: I gave her infected ribosomes--the grossest possible error that you could make in an experiment like that..... We were there at the right place, we were doing the right things, but I was doing things as an amateur--stupid and sloppy. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; At this point in the story, Feynman is interested in biology and working with ribosomes. If it doesn't ring any bells, the chapter is called &quot;A Map of the Cat?&quot;. Admitting your mistake on paper should be an easy thing to do. However, in the real world, it's not that easy. I can attest from personal experience that swallowing your pride and admitting you are wrong is really hard. But it's definitely one of the most enriching experiences I've had in my life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; #2: Reminds me of my early M.Sc days :) &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    So I prepared the talk, and when the day came, I went in and did something that young men who have had no experience in giving talks often do—I put too many equations up on the blackboard. You see, a young fella doesn’t know how to say, “Of course, that varies inversely, and this goes this way…” because everybody listening already knows; they can see it. But he doesn’t know. He can only make it come out by actually doing the algebra—and therefore the reams of equations. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; This is so true! My first talk in Alberta was such a disaster! I had given a few tech talks in my undergrad before. Since the bar was so low in Trichy, I thought I was doing great. But it was the exact opposite in Alberta. They wanted to understand my project and were at the seminars primarily because of a scientific curiosity. It's also daunting when some of the great minds on campus are coming to see your talk. I did get better at giving talks later on. There is still a lot of scope for improvement, but the early memories which weren't so pleasant back then bring a smile to my face now :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; #3: Question everything, truly understand the subject, don't fall for fancy titles and reputation &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    But then a miracle occurred, as it has occurred again and again in my life, and it’s very lucky for me: the moment I start to think about the physics, and have to concentrate on what I’m explaining, nothing else occupies my mind—I’m completely immune to being nervous. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; I've lost count of the number of times I've pretended to understand something just to appear smart. Sometimes I've accepted ideas in a paper just because they were written by a reputed professor or a student from a world-class university. Thanks to my lucky stars, I've had the pleasure of working with some great scientists at the University of Alberta and Kindred. Time and time again, they taught me this valuable lesson - &quot;You're a researcher. That means you need to ask the hard questions and report the results dutifully. You should not accept results just because some big wig says so. If you aren't completely convinced that the idea, approach and methodology is right, that work is unacceptable.&quot; That lesson right there is essential to being a good researcher. Now what does that have to do with excerpt #3? Well, unless you are convinced about your work, it's impossible to think just about the research and then concentrate on what you are explaining. You must have a lot of nerve to disagree with legends in a field and openly speak up. If you aren't convinced that you are absolutely right, the choice to disagree doesn't even exist. Interestingly, Feynman says that he'd never make the mistake of reading experts opinions when he recollects the story about finding the right laws of beta decay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; #4 &amp;amp; #5: Learn to say no. You do not have to live up to someone else's expectation &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    You know, what they think of you is so fantastic, it's impossible to live up to it. You have no responsibility to live up to it!&quot; 
    It was a brilliant idea: You have no responsibility to live up to what other people think you ought to accomplish. I have no responsibility to be like they expect me to be. It's their mistake, not my failing.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; This is one of those cliched life lessons that's been said time and time again to all of us. Great to see that someone actually internalized this :) Feynman's letter to refuse a terrific offer from Chicago is downright hilarious!     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    About a month later I was at a meeting, and Leona Marshall came over and said, &quot;It's funny you didn't accept our offer at Chicago. We were so disappointed, and we couldn't understand how you could turn down such a terrific offer.&quot;
    
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    
    &quot;It was easy,&quot; I said, &quot;because I never let them tell me what the offer was.&quot; A week later I got a letter from her. I opened it, and the first sentence said, &quot;The salary they were offering was--,&quot; a tremendous amount of money, three or four times what I was making. Staggering! Her letter continued, &quot;I told you the salary before you could read any further. Maybe now you want to reconsider, because they've told me the position is still open, and we'd very much like to have you.&quot;
    
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 
    
    So I wrote them back a letter that said, &quot;After reading the salary, I've decided that I must refuse. The reason I have to refuse a salary like that is I would be able to do what I've always wanted to do -- get a wonderful mistress, put her up in an apartment, buy her nice things.. . With the salary you have offered, I could actually do that, and I know what would happen to me. I'd worry about her, what she's doing; I'd get into arguments when I come home, and so on. All this bother would make me uncomfortable and unhappy. I wouldn't be able to do physics well, and it would be a big mess! What I've always wanted to do would be bad for me, so I've decided that I can't accept your offer.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; #6: Medicine, law, business, engineering, these are noble pursuits and necessary to sustain life. But poetry, beauty, romance, love, these are what we stay alive for &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    I understood at last what art is really for, at least in certain respects. It gives somebody, individually, pleasure. You can make something that somebody likes so much that they’re depressed, or they’re happy, on account of that damn thing you made! In science, it’s sort of general and large: You don’t know the individuals who have appreciated it directly....
    
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    
    I understood that to sell a drawing is not to make money, but to be sure that it’s in the home of someone who really wants it; someone who would feel bad if they didn’t have it. This was interesting.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Alright, I couldn't resist quoting Robin Williams from dead poets society. But it's still true! I'm an engineer myself. There's a lot of beauty to science. But it's a different kind of beauty. It evokes different kind of passion. But art, music, etc., have the potential to stir up an entirely different set of powerful emotions :)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;#7: Ignorance is fixable. But pompous dickery is just terrible! &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    There were a lot of fools at that conference—pompous fools—and pompous fools drive me up the wall. Ordinary fools are all right; you can talk to them, and try to help them out. But pompous fools—guys who are fools and are covering it all over and impressing people as to how wonderful they are with all this hocus pocus—THAT, I CANNOT STAND! An ordinary fool isn’t a faker; an honest fool is all right. But a dishonest fool is terrible!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;  Feynman can't stand pretentious idiots either! Yay! :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; #8: MUST READ: Feynman's take on Scientific Integrity &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    It’s a kind of scientific integrity, a principle of scientific thought that corresponds to a kind of utter honesty—a kind of leaning over backwards. For example, if you’re doing an experiment, you should report everything that you think might make it invalid—not only what you think is right about it: other causes that could possibly explain your results; and things you thought of that you’ve eliminated by some other experiment, and how they worked—to make sure the other fellow can tell they have been eliminated. Details that could throw doubt on your interpretation must be given, if you know them. You must do the best you can—if you know anything at all wrong, or possibly wrong—to explain it. If you make a theory, for example, and advertise it, or put it out, then you must also put down all the facts that disagree with it, as well as those that agree with it. There is also a more subtle problem. When you have put a lot of ideas together to make an elaborate theory, you want to make sure, when explaining what it fits, that those things it fits are not just the things that gave you the idea for the theory; but that the finished theory makes something else come out right, in addition. In summary, the idea is to try to give all of the information to help others to judge the value of your contribution; not just the information that leads to judgment in one particular direction or another.
   
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;

    We’ve learned from experience that the truth will out. Other experimenters will repeat your experiment and find out whether you were wrong or right. Nature’s phenomena will agree or they’ll disagree with your theory. And, although you may gain some temporary fame and excitement, you will not gain a good reputation as a scientist if you haven’t tried to be very careful in this kind of work. And it’s this type of integrity, this kind of care not to fool yourself, that is missing to a large extent in much of the research in cargo cult science.
    
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;

    The first principle is that you must not fool yourself—and you are the easiest person to fool. So you have to be very careful about that. After you’ve not fooled yourself, it’s easy not to fool other scientists. You just have to be honest in a conventional way after that.
    
    &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;

    So I have just one wish for you—the good luck to be somewhere where you are free to maintain the kind of integrity I have described, and where you do not feel forced by a need to maintain your position in the organization, or financial support, or so on, to lose your integrity. May you have that freedom.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt; #9: Adventures require effort and patience :) &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    I had a way of having adventures which is hard to explain: it’s like fishing, where you put a line out and then you have to have patience. When I would tell someone about some of my adventures, they might say, “Oh, come on—let’s do that!” So we would go to a bar to see if something will happen, and they would lose patience after twenty minutes or so. You have to spend a couple of days before something happens, on average. I spent a lot of time talking to show girls. One would introduce me to another, and after a while, something interesting would often happen.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 13:40:29 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//musings/excerpts-surely-you-are-joking-mr-feynman/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//musings/excerpts-surely-you-are-joking-mr-feynman/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Surely You're Joking Mr. Feynman: Adventures of a Curious Character</title>
        <description>&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Richard P. Feynman is wonderfully weird :) I see a lot of people describing him as an eccentric genius. I disagree. He's a genius alright. But eccentric doesn't capture his joie de vivre. He had the guts to live life on his own terms while most of us succumb to peer pressure. The reminiscences of Ralph Leighton are quite possibly the watered down versions of actual events. If such recollections can make my eyes go wide in wonder and laugh heartily, watching Feynman in action would've been inspiring/entertaining to say the least! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; A human being should be able to change a diaper, plan an invasion, butcher a hog, conn a ship, design a building, write a sonnet, balance accounts, build a wall, set a bone, comfort the dying, take orders, give orders, cooperate, act alone, solve equations, analyze a new problem, pitch manure, program a computer, cook a tasty meal, fight efficiently, die gallantly. Specialization is for insects. 
&lt;br /&gt;
― Robert A. Heinlein 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; I couldn't fit Feynman into specific &quot;boxes&quot;. He's a legendary physicist, good artist, talented musician (drums, frigideira, bongo), &quot;expert&quot; safecracker, possibly a great dancer and unbelievably good at social situations. I know hardly few people who are as versatile as he is. But Feynman is still on a different level of excellence. What makes Feynman one of the greatest humans to have ever lived? I couldn't figure it out for a while. I took a moment to think about my favourite stories from his life. All of a sudden, it dawned on me. He took his work seriously, but never took himself seriously! Whatever he did, he poured his heart and soul into it. If he was intrigued by something, he played along until his curiosity was satiated. If we wanted to do something, he just did it. He just didn't give a fuck about what other people think or say about him. No wonder he couldn't stand pretension and hypocrisy! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; I watched Yes Man starring Jim Carrey recently. It's a predictable comedy. Nevertheless it's a hilarious movie with an oft-forgotten message - open up your mind to other possibilities and say yes when a great/fun opportunity arises. I believe Feynman truly mastered this concept. That's exactly why his life was so much fun! Ralph Leighton's words perfectly capture my thoughts on Feynman's life - &quot;That one person could have so many wonderfully crazy things happen to him in one life is sometimes hard to believe. That one person could invent so much innocent mischief in one life is surely an inspiration!&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; If someone asks me what portions of the book were my favourites, I'd mention the following fantastic/crazy encounters in Feynman's life: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Interactions with other legendary scientists at Princeton and Los Alamos &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Stories on playing the frigideira with a Brazilian Samba school &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Criticism of the Brazilian education system (somethning that is quite relevant to India as well) &lt;/li&gt; 
    &lt;li&gt; His antics trying to learn art, practicing drawing at a topless restaurant and later commissioned to draw a nude toreador girl being charged by a bull with a man's head &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Learning to play African drums music, then drumming for an all percussion ballet! &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Burning out and then doing science for fun (the plate wobbling story at Cornell) &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; Antics involving Las Vegas show girls &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; The chapters titled &quot;An Offer You Must Refuse&quot; and &quot;Cargo Cult Science&quot; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; This book has been in my shelf for more than 2 years now. I finally got around to reading it :) I don't regret not reading it earlier. I think I read this book at the right time in my life - When I was finally ready for it, when I could finally appreciate what it means to live a full life. This book is going on my list of all time favourites :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Rating: 5/5 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;major&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; &lt;b&gt;P.S: &lt;/b&gt; In an effort to avoid spoilers, I did not talk about specific stories or excerpts from the book. If you are interested in reading such a post, please find it &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/musings/excerpts-surely-you-are-joking-mr-feynman/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 10:42:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//bookreviews/surely-you-are-joking-mr-feynman/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//bookreviews/surely-you-are-joking-mr-feynman/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ball Drop At Times Square: DON'T DO IT! </title>
        <description>&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; New York City is awesome! It's got an amazing nightlife, mesmerizing views of the skyline and great food. There's tons of stuff to do in the city. I loved roaming around Manhattan, strolling in the Empire State building, watching the indescribable, wacky Blue Man Group show and bunch of other stuff. Times Square is quite something to experience around midnight. Would recommend doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; A friend of mine dragged me along to watch the ball drop at Times Square on New Years eve. It was horrible. We stood in a long queue for hours wearing a poncho to shelter us from the rain. It was freezing, raining and ridiculously overcrowded. I hated it all. In a twisted sense, it gives me some confidence. If I could tolerate soaking boots, freezing weather in complete boredom, all for a stupid celebration, I could definitely do great things if I'm motivated for the right reasons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; On a closing note, don't do it! Do not go for a public viewing of the ball drop. It was a miserable experience for me. Completely useless. It's amazing to see how many people participate in the delusion. Everyone over there wanted to believe it was some special, life-changing experience because the media says so. Go party with friends, travel to a different country or spend time with family instead! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 13:02:55 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//traveldiaries/random/nyc-balldrop-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//traveldiaries/random/nyc-balldrop-2019/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bossypants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Tina Fey is … funny :) Full disclosure - before reading this book, I had no idea who Tine Fey is. I just read the book since a lot of the people I follow on goodreads seemed to like it. I liked the fact that she didn’t take herself too seriously in the book. It was mostly silly, tongue-in-cheek humour that makes you chuckle. A quick, light-hearted read that feels like a chat with a friend over beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rating: 3.5/5&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 20:45:57 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//bookreviews/bossypants/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//bookreviews/bossypants/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zone Of Proximal Development</title>
        <description>&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; For a brief period in undergrad, my friends and I used to play FIFA on our laptops. It's great to have your own in-house LAN tournaments. We did it once in a while just to kill time and chill out. Did I also mention that it's a lot of fun? Anyways, I sucked big time when we started out. The good thing was all my friends sucked at it as well. It helped level the playing field. One particular hot and miserable Trichy afternoon, my roommate (Naresh) and I were playing FIFA on our own laptops against the PC. I paused my game to see how he was doing. I think he was trailing by a goal or so, but then mentioned something interesting. He was playing with the difficulty set to Professional. No wonder he was behind! Btw, I was killing it in Semi-Pro :P When I asked him why, he said sem-pro was easy and world-class was too hard. So he picked a happy medium - a level which he could win at sometimes, but has to slog through to barely keep up. All this happened in a nonchalant manner. I would've probably forgotten that conversation if I hadn't tried what he said. I increased the difficulty of my games and lost way more often. But when I went to play with my friends, I was doing way better! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row uniform&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/comfort-stretch-panic.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Be it fitness activities or practice coding tests, I've always found that I learned best when I was in the stretch zone. In all these situations, we already have a set of skills that can be further improved with practice and effort. But self-guided training in itself may not be optimal. Sometimes, a friend or a teacher was able to help me whenever I got stuck. They were able to pin-point my mistakes accurately and further improved my capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Later, I came across an article about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zone_of_proximal_development&quot;&gt;Zone of Proximal Development&lt;/a&gt; introduced by the psychologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lev_Vygotsky&quot;&gt;Lev Vygotsky&lt;/a&gt;. According to this theory, we learn fast when guided by those who are more knowledgeable and skilled. Intuitively it  makes sense. I can personally attest to the fact that working hard with/under the guidance of smart people is the fastest way to learn. Atleast, that's the fastest way I've ever learned. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row uniform&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/zone-of-proximal-development.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; There are three factors that are essential to this learning process: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;The Expert:&lt;/b&gt; Typically someone who is more knowledgebale about the topic than the learner. The &quot;expert&quot; provides critical feedback and guidance crucial for learning and development. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Social Interaction:&lt;/b&gt; It's easy to imagine a parent or a teacher as the expert. But that's not always the case. In many instances, friends and colleagues go out of their way to help us out. In essense, a good peer group is crucial to the learning process.  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Scaffolding:&lt;/b&gt; Typically, in school, teachers provide appropriate assistance and tools to accomplish a new task or skill. These activities, instructions, tools, and resources are known as scaffolding. Just like a newly constructed building, the scaffolding is evenutally removed once the student is able to complete the task independently. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Neat little theory isn't it :) In summary, break down the task into small, doable chunks that push you out of your comfort zone, work in a collaborative environment with smart folks and enjoy the process! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 09:43:27 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//musings/zone-of-proximal-development/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//musings/zone-of-proximal-development/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Happy New Year Folks! (2019)</title>
        <description>&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; We humans are a strange species. We come up with weird excuses to party and have fun. Every year, we celebrate Earth completing it's orbit around the Sun. I love it! There's a rekindled sense of optimism in the air. It gives us time to reflect over the last 12 months and take stock of our life. A nice checkpoint in what would hopefully be an amazing life :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; It's been a great year with a lot of ups and downs, of highs and lows. It tested my sanity, strengthened my resolve and made me truly appreciate the value of friends and family. It truly was a landmark year that would forever remain close to my heart. Here's to a year that has given me a lot, that has probably taken more, but overall a year that has been my biggest learning curve yet. I'm grateful for it all. Eternally indebted to a lot of people in my life for their kindness and affection. A special shoutout to the following things and people in my life this year (in no particular order): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The amazing Kindred team (especially my colleagues James, Rupam and Dima) - The AI Research team is awesome! Great, down-to-earth colleagues, quality work and a nurturing work environment. They’ve helped me grow a lot as a researcher.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One of my closest friends SV (Vignesh Sk) - One of the kindest, smartest, wackiest guys I know. Talks openly from his heart, completely candid and most importantly, a great friend :) If not for him and my work at Kindred, I shudder to imagine how my life could’ve turned out this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Naresh, Raam, Boxer and TSB - My long time friends from NIT. My comrades in arms. Always grateful to our inane, funny and sometimes deeply philosophical conversations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PV (Vignesh Pasupathy) - This guy is the definition of smart, unassuming and humble. While we don’t talk as often as we should, we’ve got a great thing going. The conversation starts where we left off previously :)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Francois Hogan - Had an amazing time working with him during his internship at Kindred. Super smart, digs deep until he truly understands what he studies, runs marathons and always smiling and humble :) Unfortunate that he had to go back to MIT to finish his PhD :)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pooja, Ashmini and Megan - Hard to describe, some wonderful memories :)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vishaal and Ramkumar - Some of my oldest friends from high school. Super smart, fun guys to hangout with! They’re both living in Pittsburgh (roommates) and pursuing a PhD. I had a blast hanging out with them in Sept this year!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharath Anna - A cousin who’s life experiences would blow your mind! Never got a chance to spend time with him until this year. Great guy who I’d love to josh around with more often.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rajan uncle - My Dad’s closest friend. Another guy who’s life experiences, tastes and ideas impressed the hell out of me. Kind, funny and unassuming :) The trip to Vellore to meet him would always be close to my heart :)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Honorable mentions - Dinesh, Adhav, Raghu, Navaneeth, Sanket, Megha, Jeremy, Simge, Dieta, Bala, Hema, Cheryl-Ann, Chris Glover, Lalith and Siddharth Balan for being in my life. Yoga classes with Alejandra. Colin (intern at Kindred) for exhibiting true emotional strength. Also the family run Dumpling House in East Chinatown!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paati, Senthil, Nathan and Rajesh Chithappa, Anitha Chithi, Sriram, Karthik and Varshini - For their genuine love and concern for me :)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Srinath - My brother who puts up with all the weird shit I say. He’s currently studying in Sweden. I’m sure he’s going to do great things in life :)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amma and Appa - Eternally indebted to their unconditional love. I do debate with them a lot just for the sake of it :P They really did let me live life on my own terms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt; Wishing everyone reading this a happy 2019 :) Hopefully, you have a prosperous year ahead filled with love, acceptance and loads of fun :) &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 20:57:55 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//random/happy-new-year-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//random/happy-new-year-2019/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>